this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
hello this is justin baier for software
engineering radio and today i'm speaking
with aaron reinhardt
aaron is expanding the possibilities of
chaos engineering to cyber security
he began pioneering security and chaos
engineering as chief security architect
at united health group
uhg while at uhg reinhardt released
chaos slinger
reinhardt recently founded a ks
engineering startup called varico with
casey rosenthal from netflix
and is a frequent author consultant and
speaker in the space welcome to the show
aaron
thanks for having me of course so just
for our listeners
if you're not familiar at all with chaos
engineering i want to refer you back to
episode 325 where we discuss chaos
engineering with tammy patel
but aaron just to start off the episode
is a quick refresher
can you kind of give us a quick overview
of the goals of chaos engineering as an
overall discipline
and then a little bit into how sce
security chaos engineering
fits into that overall set of goals sure
you know i like to
you know there's a netflix definition uh
the original definition of chaos
engineering but
because i can kind of start with my
definition oh it's because it's not it's
a
just the way i like to interpret it for
people it's the idea of proactively
introducing turbulent conditions
into a distributed system to try to
determine the conditions by which a
system or service will fail
before it actually fails so the
fundamental premise of the problem is is
that
we're learning about how our systems
actually work through
surprises right it wasn't a surprise of
meeting an outage or an incident we
should would have fixed it right because
we would have known about the problem
right well the thing we didn't know
about the problem so we couldn't fix it
so it's just
it's a surprise but these surprises come
in a caustic uh that's customer
as customer pain uh and chaos
engineering kind of allows you to
be proactive about that surface that
failure before it manifests the
customer pain so it's not about causing
gas it's about
creating order yeah it's almost that
controlled detonation in your
environment to ensure
you're not creating an unsafe
environment you already know that
there's hidden things but
let's find them before they come out and
surprise you
precisely precisely can you kind of
discuss
what the goal of security chaos
engineering is within that overall chaos
engineering
concept well it's kind of the same so i
mean so throughout my career
i've been a builder been a builder most
of my career before i got into security
and um so you can never really kind of
uh lie to me how things are built i kind
of know things are just you know
uh barely put together you know because
i mean that's i mean for software
engineering is a process of
that didn't work that didn't work uh oh
boy that kind of works you know but
you know it's not a it's a messy very
messy thing but it's like
that's that's how i mean the whole camp
back explore expanded track right it's
like you know exploration
and experimentation core part of
building things you know and um
so i've always looked at security as an
engineering problem in my from my
perspective in my opinion
it still is an engineering problem it
always has been so when i look at uh
when i saw chaos engineering
like it made so much sense to me as a
security practitioner like
you know it's not security is not a
separate part of the system
it's the system is either secure or it's
not so
uh well the fundamental problems that
we're trying to solve with chaos
engineering security
is the is is really the builder the
builder um
the security and the build process not
not built process but the
the um so what happens is that uh
systems need a certain amount of
flexibility for a builder to change
something right so that need to be
flexible and constantly change something
comes up against uh the fact that
security needs context in order to be
effective
right so when you change something and
you're constantly changing it the
security mechanism apparatus has to
change with it
the problem is is that that's not
happening uh and uh you you put
that context of this problem set in a
world of high speed and high scale um
you know the problem just
bifurcates right it just goes in two
different directions and and what we're
doing with chaos
against gas engineering for security is
really the same sort of thing we do
for availability and general brittleness
of a system is
we're asking the system a question right
i've hey system
or hey security i believe under
condition x
when x occurs you're tasked to do y
now when x occurs does y actually happen
right and it's
i'll tell you what i have yet to ever
see a chaos engineering experiment
availability stability
or security actually succeed the first
time it was almost always wrong
about what we think the system actually
is
exactly and that's the whole point of
actually doing the testing
and i mean as you mentioned a lot of
systems end up being put together with
you know a little bit of duct tape and a
little bit of bubble gum to
stand them up and the problem is that
you know
when you look at traditional security
tools like a waf
for example a web application firewall
you know the most
basic of them all is regex you can't
keep that and actually grow that with a
rapidly developing application because
no application developer wants to write
500 waf rules
every time they roll out a new feature
to some endpoint
but kind of going down this track of you
know where sce
and traditional security are kind of
butting heads most of our listeners are
really software engineers and they're
not
necessarily in the security world and
that's not where they necessarily live
so i want to kind of discuss what some
of the traditional information security
goals and methods are
and why they don't work in agile
development environments
for example when you look at something
core
concept wise as like the cia triad
in security so let me see what do i want
to start with this so
um i um just just for context i was a
software engineer most of my career
right so i pride myself if if i identify
identify
as anything it's it's a software
engineer probably just as much as
security
person uh person professional engineer i
guess
whatever um but it's so what is this
what is the um what are the traditional
context that security chaos engineering
comes up against and
so just to be clear none of the other
testing methodologies or instrumentation
methods for
security i'm not saying you shouldn't do
any of those you still need to do pen
testing
you still need to do scanning right you
still need to do and scanning up for
static
pro issues in code you need uh you need
to still do runtime based assessments
the problem that we're dealing with is
the post deployment complexity issue
right is that it's it's not so much to
build process we're really addressing
with there are other methodologies that
are already addressing those problems
what we're dealing with the sheer amount
of complexity in the post deployment
for example let's take a 10 micro
service healthcare application
right so you've got rx uh you've got rx
service you've got a claim service
you've got 10 services right you don't
actually probably have 10
right well let's keep in mind you
probably have a different set of humans
for every service
right uh and they're probably seen maybe
on the same schedule maybe not
but close right uh and you probably
coming back to you don't just have 10
probably because for throughput reasons
you might have
five to ten of each right that's already
you're looking at fifty to a hundred
right
uh we're not even started yet like
microservices are interdependent
they're not meaning that they're not
independent they're dependent upon other
services for functionality
and um uh to operate while sometimes you
need to have
older versions of microservices running
to support other services
also you'll have some older versions
running and you know if uh if
you know you might be rolling um some
blue green type of deployments
right so you might have some newer
versions right so we're already talking
about two threaded microservices we
haven't
started adding any weird complexity to
this problem right it's very difficult
for humans to mentally model that
behavior
right like but think about these humans
we're constantly releasing and changing
things
like are we all aware what all the uh
how how all the context of the system is
changing
on a constant basis we're not right this
system
is slowly drifting what city decker
calls slowly drifting into a state of
unknown right
is that you know and we don't find out
what we didn't know what was really
happening in that system until we have
an outage
or an incident you know and that that's
painful to customers
we don't have to we don't have to
encounter these problems percent
right chaos engineering is a corrective
methodology that so
about coming back to the security
question right so what we're doing is
we're
uh let's say we have containers you know
docker container or kubernetes type of
security solutions
um you know uh like aqua twist law
encapsulate whatever whatever you want
to pick
um i'm not picking on anybody right but
like um
just that solution all the other testing
you put in place
is all that is like the whole goal we're
trying to achieve is like
did all that mean anything right like we
did all that testing put all these
controls in place we put all these
firewalls all these
uh change configuration management type
of detection tools
like do those things actually function
when they're needed
right because finding out during a
security incident or a breach is not a
very effective
uh you know way of detecting that right
and it's hard it's hard because what
happens is it's like
you know uh the security instant
response process is very subjective
right
no matter how much money you spend on
security or how many people you hire you
have the best and brightest
you still don't know a lot you don't
know when it's gonna happen why it's
happening who's trying to get in
how they're going to get in you're
hoping all hoping all the things you put
into place
actually function when they're supposed
to function you know and
engineers this is like something i love
to say it's like engineers no matter
what discipline of engineering
uh it is we don't believe in hope our
luck right we build it it works or it
doesn't and instrumentation
uh tells us otherwise in the data we get
from instrumentation it's the feedback
but which in the by which we build
context to improve what we built
uh and that's what we're trying to
achieve for security so for example i
have that
firewall in place that the fire will
actually detect a block
a misconfigurated port change right like
solving that problem for 35 years right
like you know uh there's no reason why
that should happen
did the fire will provide good context
to the to the instant response process
right like did it throw an alert did
they could they read
what really drives me nuts is like when
when alerts
are when log data doesn't make sense to
a human
like we've forgotten that was the point
to begin with
right like it's supposed to tell us what
went wrong
right or like so we have the context and
awareness to fix it
exactly having your system that spits
out 500
json objects every 20 seconds whenever a
user hits any endpoint on the service
isn't going to provide you any useful
security context
unless you're looking for very specific
key activity indicators
within that and as we've kind of alluded
to throughout the show
when you start piling on 5 10
15 20 controls because you have a little
bit of hipaa over here and a little bit
of pci over here so you
went check box security and went down
the list and said well i file integrity
monitoring i have a firewall that blocks
it
if that doesn't all come together
somewhere it doesn't
help so how does sce help fix
some of that what it does is it really
helps us kind of
uh instrument that that ecosystem that
we're not talking about post deployment
it asked a question i'm
honest to god i really started doing
this uh years ago united health group
i mean this is after i sort of was part
of leading the devops transformation
there and the cloud transformation
very new to aws at the time i've been
through cloud transformation before
i just knew the kind of problem since i
was coming up against them like then i
saw this thing that
uh we hired our first sre uh and he
started talking about this thing called
chaos engineering i'm like
oh should this i think i think this
could help me i think this could help me
with my problem my problem is the chief
security architect united health group
was
is that people would come to me with
like you'd have a master data architect
and a solutions architect for an
application come to me with two
different diagrams of the same system
it's like it represents their mental
model in their context of how they view
the system
well um you know i could it's hard for
me to design good security
but i don't have an accurate reflection
of what the system actually is
it was always concerned i'm very
passionate about my work very passionate
about the craft like
i want my work to to be effective i want
it to be helpful i want to add value
and i was never sure right if like
i actually have the right information or
my guidance i gave them was actually
correct because security
placement configuration of security
controls truly matters remember their
security
controls are context dependent and so
what i needed a way to do is skip
through all the humans in the process
and ask the computer questions
right i say hey you know when x
condition occurs
right when s3 bucket is launched uh
without encryption
are like or with the wrong kind of
encryption or like
or a misconfigured port is uh happens
like
are we detecting that right like these
are very simple things you know i've
actually found all chaos experiments
like it's kind of like what they say
about martial arts right is that like if
you get one move right and you're like
an expert at one move
like you know like you're almost
untouchable it's kind of the same thing
with chaos engineering i found
it's like you get one simple experiment
you can run so many times different
environments
it tells you all different kinds of
things right i mean like you can look at
the
observability which in my opinion is
still one of the biggest unsolved
problems in security
is software security observability is
horrific
right um and you know there's not a
whole lot of people approaching that
problem
but with chaos engineering it's one way
to help you find out like how helpful
like
there's when i first started doing this
uh there's a woman at
pinterest she's moved on since then her
name was primaverani she actually wrote
one of the use cases in the book in the
o'reilly book
she started taking a security kiosk
experiments
and started turning off micro logging on
microservices their assumption was is
that they'd immediately detect that kind
of behavior
and it would be an honest shoe like
they'd be able to fix it respond to it
well they didn't you know and i argue
probably most people out here wouldn't
either
uh because most people look at log
volume they don't look at individual log
logging services
you know i thought that was interesting
yeah it's almost that
and we're gonna kind of cover this a
little bit later in how you're designing
your sce
experiments and your processes but as
you kind of mentioned
just early on there with the
architecture conversation you can have
six architects in a room and they all
might have generally the same diagram
but that's not gonna reflect reality
when it gets actually deployed to aws
and then you can use the aws tools and
think that you're detecting every time
somebody puts up an s3 bucket that's
public but
maybe you were only detecting if they
initially deployed it and made it public
but not if they changed it later
or if someone went in after the fact and
put up another service that had public
access and was copying data over between
the s3 pockets
and there's so many different rabbit
holes that you can go down with that
whole concept and we're going to discuss
a little bit later when we talk about
threat modeling with sce
but i kind of want to go back to your
point there with
observability in security how does
sce provide a little bit better
observability and
even some better metrics around
information security
um i mean so to keep in mind like i am
still
uh well the context i'm giving everyone
out here is like you know
just outside of the beginning of this
whole this whole
this whole uh expansion of chaos
engineering security so i'm
don't think these are the bounds by
which you can only do this i'm still
learning
other companies have been applying i'm
like wow why didn't you tell me that i
would love to learn more about that like
anyway so some of the ways that like i
found uh so observability and metrics
right
some of some some uh some cool nuggets i
found and using it for those
things is um observability right like
because it's pro-life because we're
proactively introducing
an objective signal into the subjective
process of instant response per se
like we're not waiting for an event to
occur right
we're proactively introducing a
controlled condition in the system
and we're watching it right but like we
can we can start looking at the
technology
because so when you're responding to an
event there's no time to look at the
quality of the logs
right people are probably freaking out
they're not sure if this is the one
event uh you know and you know uh people
i mean most companies that argue over
the 90
range uh are worried about the name
blame shame game that's what that's what
i like to call it it's like
what about oh that was that mean it
caused it am i gonna be blamed for it
like and
is you know my team gonna take the hit
you know whatever right like
or am i gonna be fired right like you
know um
you know but uh like when like like when
there's an incentive going on the
wardrobe comes on it's about getting the
thing back up and running in
in business continuity it's not about
like what went wrong
so we don't do chaos engineering during
that exercise
right uh what we do it is when there is
no fire
right we do it proactively and because
we're trying to
try to introduce control conditions
system to see did the log events make
sense for that misconfigured firewall or
that s3 bucket or
are are that uh uh that vulnerable
container that was launched our
vulnerable image
whatever i was like did the things work
and if they didn't
did it give us context that it from the
form of dogs and alerts
are what john oswald likes to call the
footsteps in the sand
right like you know uh which are the log
events the tracing and the
observability right uh did it tell us
what it needed we needed to know
right like to to do something about it
and but when there's an active war room
it's too late you're trying to piece
together threads uh and try to figure
things out
that's not a time to do that what we're
able to do is we're going to figure out
where our gaps are
where our visibility gaps are trying to
understand it proactively so
god forbid even if an event that's
different than this of
this construct we're injecting um we can
we'll have uh we may have better
observability for that control that we
found we had a gap on
you know and that's one of the areas you
can really help with the observability
because what is observability right
it's the idea of understanding how your
system works internally
through its external outputs right so
like if you can't understand the outputs
like you know it's not helpful right and
what really drives me nuts as an
engineer
uh is that um you'll have all these like
you know i'm not gonna pick on any
security tooling or any or any log video
like inventors out there but
there are there are vendors out there
with the ai and ml special sauce will
say
you give me all your alerts and i'll
predict the next out into their outage
that that that that is an erosion of a
fundamental premise in software is that
guess who writes log events software
engineers
right what do software engineers
prioritize features right like
we're a lot what about all the log
events that don't exist right what about
all
you does that make sense there's a lot
of data in context that you don't have
so like
my point is is like we can find out some
of these things find out these gaps
increase their visibility and and you
know
as a result better security so that's
that's just the observability piece
suggesting like some
of the other metrics measurement that i
have found useful i know
the folks at capital one and cardinal
health also have been using it for that
it's like
because we're causing these events
proactively we now have the starting
point
right to start saying like for instance
response for example you can see
do we have enough people on call for
that event did they under did the tools
work correctly
right how long did it take us to capture
that how long did it take to control to
quarantine it
like all these things like we could now
because the hard part
before is like we're waiting for
something to happen and then timing it
but just because you caught it that that
doesn't mean it wasn't a cascading or
compounding event
we rarely ever account for that in
security that it's a compounding thing
or a cascading type of failure in a
large scale distributed system
it almost always is a cascading yeah we
look at something as
simple as a dns issue
just from a service side of things and a
service availability side of things and
that can create a cascading issue
everywhere and that can even hamper your
response to it because let's say you're
using some type of proxy to access your
services so your engineers don't have to
directly access them because
you wanted to implement you know
privileged identity management
well that probably relies on dns a
little bit to figure out what systems it
needs to connect to and if that's down
you're going to have some problems there
dns you know dns certs i mean those
those you know those two go all day for
chaos experiment exactly and
just a couple more things before we
start diving into designing these things
where do you think that sce should fit
into
your security architecture your security
engineering processes
or should it be more melded into the
software development side of the house
i'll tell you where i'm seeing it you
know because i sort of kicked off a lot
of this
uh met me my co-founder another
co-founder uh co-author of the rally
book kelly kelly shortridge
she's been a huge advocate of it for a
long time and you know um
we're in the process um you know and who
uh i find it a lot of times
it makes sense to me because a lot of
people out of where it's originating in
companies is the architecture function
uh and it's like okay well yeah all
right um
you know that makes sense that's where i
started with it um but also i'm seeing
it
um you know on the product teams uh the
there's a lot of growth in people using
it for containers
right um and it has nothing to do with
aqua or twist lock or capsule or any
other market leading solution
for containers their solutions could be
100 perfect
but that doesn't mean they're always
tuned correctly they're always they're
always
uh like up to date they're always that
that that
that report hasn't been blocked so they
can't download the manifest
to identify a new a new problem right
like
um that doesn't mean the customer is
always deploying it correctly is what
i'm saying or it's always up to date
you know um if those are some areas
where i'm seeing it
all right so it's integrated more into
the architecture function which
definitely makes sense if you think
about
even from the architecture concepts of
like
designing formal proofs for an
architecture or doing
modeling to prove that a system works if
you look at more of the safety critical
side of
software engineering but in like a
normal organization
is this something that you would want to
maybe integrate into
a security champions program if you're
trying to have something like that in
your organization
you know um i i think it depends upon
the security champions
program but like i know twilio is doing
some work with that uh the uh
vladimir did some writing in the book
about it i think so we're writing
actually kelly and i the process of
writing a
big animal book for riley um on so
that's
a heads up for the end of the this next
year but uh there'll be more writing on
that
in there so architecture is is in
particular in a state of
challenge in my opinion but there's two
large scale distributed systems and
you know um and how we do security um so
i'm a bit of a conflict on how i see
architecture anymore
um but um so it's useful it's useful
for the instant response i see a lot of
instruments it's a response team getting
a lot of value from it
i see a lot of people um you know threat
hunting type of teams utilizing it
uh to try to you know because you know
you could chase threats all day but like
it's kind of like what do you have the
ability to control i know what i built
okay does that stuff work
okay does it work right because you
could you can chase threats but like
you know or you can hunt for them but
like it's kind of like the i saw the
idea of deception engineering right like
this is a huge thing i have a conflict
with
i think chaos engineering for security
enables deception engineering
so i mean like honey pots and things
like that honey pots like
in my opinion add additional overhead as
an engineer okay so
i have to manage my security of my
application or my product
and then this other i would add this
other vulnerable part of it to try to
catch an attacker right
well it's like no now i have to manage x
plus one
right instead of x right so it's like
you know like
it's about folks so where a lot of the
problem that chaos engineer security
addresses is
you know most malware most like
malicious code
is trying to it needs some kind of
low-hanging fruit to
to succeed right it's like a
misconfiguration
or like you know try it's the the idea
is
that we're trying to inject those
conditions in the system to ensure what
we had
is actually contacted before an attacker
can uh exploit that
that simple thing right uh and because
that if you look at most of the breaches
this is not advanced stuff that's
happening right it's very simple things
and it's really i don't put the figure
in anybody it's it's the crux of
the problem is the speed and scale and
that problem i described before where
builder has to be able to change
something the security has security
controls have to respond to it
and it's it's hard for humans to keep
track of all those pieces at the same
time
so what we need is a way to constantly
check that something's not slipping
through the cracks
yeah and that's definitely something
we're going to cover a little bit later
after we discuss
designing experiments making sure that
you're automating these things so it's a
continual evaluation of it
but one thing you kind of mentioned in
there is you know honey pots
i for our listeners they may not be
super familiar with that but the concept
is that it's a
vulnerable system that you're
intentionally trying to attract an
attacker
to get on so that you can either gather
their techniques
or do something to that effect or at
least detect that somebody's on your
network that shouldn't be there or is
poking around somewhere they shouldn't
be
but i used to make the joke of honey
pots you know how do i sell to an
executive
i'm going to put something on our
network that i know is going to get
hacked or that i want to get hacked
it's a hard concept to sell to a
non-security person and as you mentioned
now you're adding a whole other system
that you have to now test for with your
security chaos engineering
to verify that it doesn't have some type
of issue
at the underlying kernel level that
might allow them to gain access
underneath the actual container or what
have you
but kind of changing directions here i
want to
move into actually designing your
experiments for security chaos
engineering and we've alluded to it
throughout the episode
but just starting from the bare minimum
how do i pick which applications
i should be doing this to is it only my
business critical apps
or should it be every single service
that i have my network
i don't know i would focus on what keeps
you up at night right like so like
nothing will keep you up at night but
what do you depend upon because but with
chaos experiments
in general right what you're trying to
do is you're um
uh you do you're only executing a chaos
experiment you think is
going to be successful right you do not
inject a failure you know you're not
going to
catch what's the point in that you know
it's broken go fix it
what we're doing is we're we're
assessing something we
think it's true without a doubt in our
minds right something we depend upon
security and security we depend heavily
on firewalls we have for a long time
right they're the nice cozy thing in the
corner that like
that thing doesn't work you know because
i mean distributed systems i mean come
on we're down to like the network
software and identity as building
constructs anymore
you know and software's still taking
over those other pieces but anyway so
like
where that's why i started with chaos
slinger that's the open source tool that
we wrote at united health group
to assess the uh security of our aws
instances
uh and you know um i guess i'm getting a
bit into design here with this
um but uh is is that um we
really counted on firewall right like uh
and we um so our assumption was we wrote
this
this initial experiment called
portslinger what it did was it
proactively on an ec2
uh security group it would introduce a
misconfigured or unauthorized
support change right uh and it would
introduce it and it would
a port that was either not open or
closed and open it or close it
you know our assumption was that without
a doubt in our minds the firewalls would
detect and block it every time
right and actually opened my eyes was
as we started doing this on our
non-commercial and commercial software
environments
it only happened 60 of the time and i
was like
whoa whoa this is huge right like
because
we really we really expected this to be
like our saving
grace right like it wasn't but what was
even cooler
that's what that was the first thing we
were losing cooler was the
uh cloud native configuration management
tool caught it blocked it every time
right it's like whoa like this thing
we're not even paying for really
like is more effective than this
expensive fancy firewall
solution it wasn't a firewall solutions
problem it was it was a drift issue
drift is a real problem in all aspects
of software
you know anyway so i guess i could
finish out the rest of that but like
you know we just started learning out
like you know all these things we depend
upon
uh you know weren't as effective or more
effective actually what was really cool
a really cool thing also on uh
on this chain of events this example i
explained a lot because
this was the main this is the main
starting point for me with chaos
engineering for security
was this simple assumption right uh and
we we
learned so many different things running
it on our aws environments
uh but like uh the third thing we
expected happened
okay was that the both of those controls
with the the amazon environments would
give us good log data
right to correlate an event i was pretty
much sure that wasn't going to happen
right because we had our own homegrown
solution for doing that we built our own
security monitoring kind of solution
through logging events a big data lake
right and we anyway it actually thrown
alert it worked it was like
that's cool it worked but then when the
sock got the alert
they they got the work they're like uh
which they did us environments come
can't come from
and they're like um you know we're very
new to aws remember that like and um
they're like
uh well as an engineer you can you can
think this through you can you can map
back the ip address and figure out where
it came from
well there's something called snap which
hides the source source ip address
intentionally right so it could take 15
minutes 30 minutes three hours
right uh that's very expensive when you
when one minute of downtime is a million
dollars
right uh that could be very expensive
but we learned all these things
proactively without uh without incurring
all that pain i mean all we had to do
was add metadata a better data pointer
to the
to the alert uh and we we knew what
instance it came from
yeah anyone that has any experience
trying to backtrack
nat will understand how painful it is to
try to
backtrack an snap translation
exactly but that kind of goes into our
next point here and you kind of
mentioned
you were doing this in multiple
environments so is this something you
should be
testing in your production environment
is this something you should only be
doing
in your qa environment if you have that
or
like purely only in your development
environment
you know honestly like i see a lot of
like large companies like
you know there's obviously different
levels of risks different levels of
context that security professionals are
dealing with like versus a big bank
versus a cloud native company you know
at
silicon valley you know but here's the i
mean here's the crux of the problem
the drift that's happening in qa it's
probably happening in prague too
right like uh so but here's the thing
there is a maturity curve for all chaos
engineering this applies to security
kiosk engineering as well
is that you need to do really do the
manual chaos engineering
anytime you do a chaos experiment for
the first time it's important to get
people from the security team the
product team uh you know the
you know maybe the product uh the
engineering manager maybe somebody from
um instant response get them in the same
room like hey do we all believe
that when we introduce a misconfigured
report i'm just going to continue with
this example
that we're going to catch and block it
because we all have been a part of this
process and
to to build that and sure that happens
right so we're all under this assumption
right
and then we actually somebody in the
room will actually introduce ticket
failure
remember this isn't like a this isn't
there's something in security called
breach and attack simulation
we're not simulating this complex attack
chain of things
right this isn't an attack right people
in chaos engineering are using the word
attack
it really scares me when they do that
we're not attacking anything
right or it's failure injection we're
injecting a failure condition
into the system okay but we always start
when we do this
this manual chaos engineering exercise
i'm talking about it's called a game day
we do this in a non-profit environment a
lower environment dev
qa we do it where the stakes are kind of
low
you know uh but with the same level of
awareness
that it might be the prod of that we
would give pride because
there are a lot of stories that people
do in chaos engineering that find out
that their devices was connected to prod
right so like
there's a funny story uh casey my
co-founder he's the creator of chaos
engineering
at netflix they said we're casey we're a
bank
and we have real money on the line so we
can't do ks engineering production
right he said okay whatever so in
nonprofit uh
or in the staging if you was they what
they're gonna do was the cast experiment
was is they're gonna bring down a kafka
node
right uh they believed as soon as they
brought down a kafka node then another
one would spin back up zookeeper would
do its thing and then
it would it would be uh you know as it
would fail over in
the traffic and the messages would
continue on well um
so they went for it they actually did
that but guess what when they brought
down
the kafka node guess what happened prod
went down
pride went down right they didn't
realize they still had a pointer
like it was some kind of pointer that
was still pointing to uh to dev
like that's but that's the funny thing
it's like so yeah that's why you keep
the awareness of like
hey we're doing this like it's prod
right but the idea is
is to get to the point of what i like to
call the leap of faith
right this is what i what i call it
right is that
i believe in the tools and the controls
and methodology by which i'm injecting
failure
i've done it before i've seen it i i
trust what i'm doing
i trust that it's not that i'm
controlling the blast radius i know
where that begins and ends
uh that i understand the observability
and the the events are giving me the
context i need to make sense
of what happened with the experiment um
and that
um you know uh you know those sort of
things right
like the chaos engineering principles i
call them the rule sets
principlesofchaos.org
um but uh but then what's the leap of
faith is like
i trust what i'm doing i've done this
before now it's time to do this in
production and understand
how how big is the problem in production
and
netflix they had a very uh several
different ways of doing this
you know uh that a lot of people don't
use today
um but i'm like uh but they had
something called the chaos automation
platform
which would create which kind of created
uh a margin of safety
in the system to do this on because they
only did when they did chaos experiments
they'd do it on like
point zero one five percent of all the
traffic right they didn't all they
didn't do
all the traffic they separated the
traffic out to like reverse proxy
uh that way they could uh that way if
they were wrong
they were wrong about how the system
worked they could uh it only affected
a small subset of the user exactly kind
of going back to the whole goal of ks
engineering being reducing user pain you
obviously don't want to kill your entire
production instance because you know
you're still reading a message queue on
a
development version of kafka although
that would probably have other issues
but going back to kind of um in your
book when you discuss
developing your experiments you bring up
the concept of threat modeling
back in episode 416 we talked to adam
shostak about
you know threat modeling as a whole and
some of the different approaches
can you kind of give an example of the
approach you found the most useful when
trying to develop these security chaos
engineering experiments
threat modeling is a technique that i
mean i've used uh ultra model
experiments before
because that means it tells you where
your assets are where your threats are
who your actors might be
right modeling that out have a good
understanding where also where trust
boundaries are in the system
it's a great way to sort of prioritize
like
what controls might be the uh ones that
we count on the most
that are the closest to uh the crown
jewels in the system
um you know and that's a good way to
prioritize controls
uh and what you're gonna test because
you want to identify what you depend
upon and
what what would uh in the end i guess
well what you count on
in order to provide your security but
like another area that like other than
threat mind that i found extremely
valuable
that um there are only a few companies
in the market really
helping with this problem like jelly
laura jones formerly of netflix
um she uh she's really trying to address
this problem but like
uh there's this uh there's a statement
who said it but like past this prologue
right like so what has happened in the
past is likely to happen again
right and so like we don't we rarely
ever look back at our incident data
and i'll tell you what it's a funny
exercise to spend 30 minutes doing
if you go back and look at prior
incident data you'll find it barely any
any incidents have been really
documented
uh uh other than maybe sub ones
uh and they're still there they're hard
to make sense of what actually happened
because people move from war room to war
room to war room the war room
you know and the the documentation is
poor but like but if you go back and
look at like
what were the what were the trends what
were the themes like what what
because other than the technology
failing right other
the technologies we depend upon in the
architecture what what particular things
are
maybe maybe we weren't as confident as
we thought at a certain capability
are we maybe we're not deploying it
right we didn't deploy it right
over these other three applications
prior uh maybe
we probably want to ensure that it's
still working uh
in you know a year later in these other
environments or we haven't drifted back
to the same problem
that we had before because the
application is designed a certain way
where it doesn't line up well with the
security mechanism
right like like i find that it's good
it's a good mix right to use threat
modeling and prior incident data
to inform you know like where you should
experiment
and you should take both of those data
into the designing of an experiment in
that human process called a game day
to make sure everybody's on the same
page because it's just like the the
devops and the the cloud transformation
kind of
trans by that it's like a movement when
everyone in the room
is wrong right we're all wrong
and we all see it it's like because
because you want to point the finger at
the security guys security kind what's
the point of it i hate saying
developer i've always hated when people
call me developer i i prefer engineer
right like and i never say that word but
like that's what security people call a
software engineer called a developer
right and it's like you know um uh
anyway uh but like
everybody's pointing the finger to
everybody but you get empathy because
everything empathy is a two-way road
like you really get that two-way
transaction we're all wrong
and we're all like hey we need to do
something about this it just
it levels the playing field and it's a
great way to build
culture so you're almost kind of
implementing regression testing by using
that
postmortem data or at least what exists
of it
to inform and direct what experiments
you're doing so that
you're preventing going back to previous
issues you've had before and making sure
that you're actually
addressing the issues you had before and
it wasn't just a band-aid fix that was
in a commit
ten years ago and then someone deleted
it because they didn't think the line
was important anymore
well yeah so well just uh just uh i love
to i love to comment in that
so after you write a chaos experiment
for the first time right
you'll find you find something that
wasn't wasn't right right
and then you'll you'll go back you'll
fix it you run the experiment again
right to ensure that okay yeah we fixed
it and then our assumption about the
obvious
how the system was supposed to work
worked uh then when it when you prove
that then it becomes like a regression
test as well right
it's like continually run that and to
ensure that over time as things to
change that
it continually that the experiment is
still valid valid
so really what we're trying to do over
time is we build these experiments and
we call them verifications america but
like like we're trying we're trying to
build a safety margin of how the system
operates because the biggest problem is
software and post deployment we have
today
is you don't understand where the edge
of the system is until you fall off of
it
right and that's that's not a
comfortable feeling right well what
we're trying to do is identify the edges
and the points that lead up to failure
in the system and you can start doing
that by doing chaos engineering in a
manning
managed you know in sort of automated uh
repeated sort of way like think of think
of it as progression testing
at that point yes so how do you
move from that singular game day
scenario
into a more continuous validation
way of doing things you know so this is
all this is i don't want to get on my uh
sort of soapbox about barricade but this
is what bearcat and casey and i created
the company was for
is to take people from the point of like
what happens most people get an open
source tool
and they'll start they'll start with the
manual process of gaming exercises
not realize it may take you from one
month to
a year and a half to get to the point
where you're producing value right and
you can
because you have to be able to explain
it to executives you know it just
depends on the scale you're trying to do
this at
what we're trying to do is like bring
that netflix style of sophistication
to the market uh with with our tooling
but uh
it takes a while i mean you have to
build that maturity right so a lot of
times you'll see
product teams start with product teams
and sres will um
sort of walk them through that game day
and then you have to you know uh
the automation with a lot of automation
comes to a head and it's occurring
is through a pipeline right the csc
pipeline is where a lot of people are
executing the automation experiments
through that could be using something
open source that could be
you don't need a lot of the open source
tools out there i mean uh are really a
reflection of just chaos kind of chaos
monkeys original
tests uh but like you can you can use
bash you can use python
just simple scripting a lot of people
the security chaos engineering that's a
lot of what they're using is they're
some of them are using like the chaos
slinger framework because there was
three main three major functions in that
tool
that's sort of like either identified
the target that you're going to do the
experiment on
actually excuse the change tracks the
change of reports of what happened
uh and that's those are the kind of the
the basic functions needed for a
security chaos experiment
but like um but do you answer your
question it's the pipeline where a lot
of
the automation is being spun off from
awesome and i do want to dive into
tooling in a little bit
and discuss a little bit of that
selection between open source or
commercial and
some of the options that are out there
but can you kind of walk us through
an example of some game day scenarios
that would work
really well for like a distributed web
application
okay um so for a security kiosk
experience
let's do that um you know uh just um
just in general just just uh from a
chaos engineering
experiment you said distributed web
application so distributed systems
like are fun right like distributed fact
of distributed systems
um is where the problem lies right like
so take kafka for example
kafka embodies every problem in
distributed systems what is kafka's
number one dependency
the network being reliable right well
what does the number one fallacy
distributed system say
the network will never be reliable so
what's happening is kafka is constantly
catching up and
storing things to memory and it can try
so it gets split brain
issues a lot of times is well anyway so
uh a distributed web application you can
learn a lot by manipulating latency
uh and um you know in terms of
a general chaos experiment uh but like
for web application let's get more
specific like
in terms of like a containerized
solution let's let's say you're using
containers most people are probably
using containers or emis
um with the container you know a simple
experiment could be a vulnerable image
just a vulnerable image launching that
into a kubernetes cluster
uh and timing how all it takes how long
did it take for the security solution to
detect it
it might detect a day one you know
actually um
i know i may have known a company that
that has a product that does this
uh in many different flavors or fashions
uh and
the solutions are not actually catching
it
and it's it sounds something like
something so easy soloing
for it's so trivial it's simple
vulnerable container
uh and and you know uh you can change
you can make it a port
that's vulnerable a deprecated piece of
software you can get what you get
creative with it right in the container
but these solutions that are charged
with detecting those capabilities from a
static or runtime perspective
should be should detect it immediately
what happens if it doesn't
because i'll tell you right it's it's
somewhere between 20 30 that's actually
i've actually found that
that's working uh and it's been an
interesting thing
for that's not just my own experiments
experience that's also the people doing
uh that uh that have reached out to me
at different companies that are doing
security cast experiments with stuff is
and like i said it's not that the
security solutions fault it's
it's that like you know it's security we
we build with kind of a state in mind
we're not not with the fact that our
soft modern software's
sort of stateless uh and you know and we
don't account for that statelessness and
there's the drift makes that occur like
but
knowing about it is part of the battle
right and that's
so that watching a vulnerable image
periodically you know you could do it
from a pipeline you could you could you
can get creative on how you would do
that's not that hard to figure out how
you would
build that uh but like it'll tell you a
lot about whether or not the security
because if it can't detect something
simple it probably can't detect
something very advanced
either so it's a good idea to just
constantly
keep a pulse on that if that makes sense
as an example
essentially you want to start with what
would be generally
simple problems that your deployed
controls should be able to solve
move those from a manual check and into
a more
continuous check and then you're
validating that that
verification process is actually still
working correctly and that you know your
security solution isn't actually
starting to drift the other way and
being less detecting of it you bring up
a
let me just say you bring up a really
good point right
simplicity very simple
very small repetitive over time the kind
of variations you get in response
like are like if you do too many complex
things at once
it gets quickly gets very easy to
understand what the heck happened
right like you can you can you're really
it's also a way to obsess the
observability in different context of
that control
uh so but like simplicity is so key i
just i'm glad you said that because
that's what distinguishing features
between
red teaming purple teaming breaching
attack simulation the security color
wheel
right like you know i feel like i'm
adding more problems to this like people
have asked me like
aaron what color are you gonna pick i'm
like no color like
i just it's not your rejection i don't
it's not breach attack simulation
it's i'm not launching a bitcoin mining
attack or the node.js
assign i'm not like i'm just injecting
one simple thing
i'm asking the system a simple thing
right and and that's that's an important
aspect
yeah and you bring up a really good
point there i mean when you look at
these larger
security testing methodologies or
frameworks
it really is about let's take an
attacker's perspective and attack it
and see what breaks and then let's see
if security detects it
but as you're kind of talking about this
it sounds like
there's a very specific
but also general set of applications
that are going to benefit from
implementing security chaos engineering
is it really like
targeted to cloud applications or large
distributed systems
or service oriented architectures with
tons of micro services
or is this something that you could do
with you know a more monolithic
application or more on-prem
applications you know i people ask that
question
uh and it's not the first time i've got
this one it's just like i
i'm i'm honest right like uh i haven't
done a lot in a lot of your traditional
applications
i'll be concerned and i might say you
can't do it right
just like people ask the same question
about chaos engineering in general
i know some of the largest banks in the
world who do chaos engineering on the
mainframe
right and it's like whoa what are you
doing
you know how does that work you know uh
well like
you know i haven't done a whole lot on
traditional monolith like a three three
tier app or like
you know um you know but uh you know
because
it's what is it reversibility is a key
aspect that you have to take into
account
meaning like uh could i just read a poi
can i could i read a point and you know
because when i find out there's a
problem or something breaks
can i quickly fix it right uh that's
what also accounting for the blast
radius
the more our more modern systems use
more of a software framework or
construct for
deployment of not only the application
level things but also the infrastructure
that supports it
you know you're able to quickly sort of
um if there's a problem with the
experiment you're able to quickly
resolve it
you know but this is typically what you
should be working out before you do it
in a production environment
but um i i i can't really
comment on the monolithic stuff just i
but i want to say though
i'm not saying don't do it but i just
say do it with care
but like the same problems that i'm
talking about in terms of the need to
change and be flexible
in a security context keeping up with
that change still existed back in the
three-tier app
and i might like i used to write i used
to write applications in in the
three-tier app world
and you know uh not everybody knows
what's going on
right knowledge only still resides with
a few people and the
the you know the system still has
emergent properties uh that not everyone
was aware of yeah and with a monolith
it in my head at least conflicts
directly with that concept of being able
to control blast radius
it's very hard in a monolith to inject
some type of failure and not
break everything downstream especially
when you look at some of the more
traditional monoliths where
it's heavily database reliant or it's
heavily
web server reliant if you break the
database
that app's going down there there's no
if and buts or questions about it
there's no circuit breakers there's no
there's no fancy
right here yeah there's no fancy uh
failovers it's
just down exactly and you're almost at
that point relying on you know the
database product to fail over correctly
for you
to save your application but kind of
changing directions here moving out of
the planning here let's talk a little
bit about tooling i know you've
mentioned
earlier um with your products where that
kind of fits in
but i kind of want to look at this from
a very high level how do i as an
organization
select the route that i want to go for
carrying these out you know how do i
decide
is this a i need to go buy a commercial
solution i should use chaos monkey from
netflix and just tweak it
or i should just use some python scripts
and that's how i'm going to do my
security chaos engineering
i honestly think that so i if i were to
do this
over again well there when i was doing
this there wasn't a whole lot of
commercial tooling right
there to do it um especially not the
security chaos stuff
uh and you know i would try to i would
procure a buy
solution that covered some of the basic
use cases right
i mean like there's so many people
building the same open source tools over
and over and over again
it's like there are 10 things out there
already on github that
already do that right like great it's
another one
right so it's like uh how many
kubernetes they're like
10 different tools that kill a pod right
you really don't need to write you don't
really don't need an open source tool to
do that right you could kill a pod
you know uh with a simple script right
um
well i really i would i would i mean
tooling as
engineers would gravitate towards the
tooling right but like it's more
important to
understand what you're doing uh
communicate to people why you're doing
it
the value in doing this uh and you know
and i would even advocate honestly
simple python
go you know um bash scripting right
uh to start right you know that way you
kind of you're writing it yourself you
kind of know what you're doing
i mean you can model it i mean i
honestly you can model it off any of the
open source tools
or there's a lot of like for aws out
there uh adrian hornsby's got a great
set of
uh scripting libraries for aws you can
use chaos slinger the tool i wrote that
for example chaos experiment i mean
really i mean the only they give you the
framework for how to do it if you just
read the code
usually the code i'm talking like maybe
a couple hundred lines of code to do
this stuff
a lot of them are lamb does right so it
makes it even simpler and cheaper to run
you know uh but like but what i want you
to do what i want people to do is be
aware of what you're doing and why
you're doing it
right but that's more important uh in my
opinion than
depict these tools aren't that
sophisticated um
it but the commercial tools out there
like are going to be
i don't want to be biased and say this
right i feel like like the inventor i've
never been a veteran before so it's like
i don't want to say oh my tool
right like uh but like it's you will get
the most of those solutions designed to
get the value quicker
right because there's different serious
studies of problems that you after you
start running cast experiments
how do you how do you communicate the
value of the results right then how do i
expand a program
right how do i like and how do i
continually write new experiments and
and don't just write experiments i don't
make up
failure modes right that that drives me
nuts but i don't just
i'm gonna kill vm i'm gonna kill pot
right like why are you doing that is
that a problem you've seen before
right is that like you know what are the
problems we're seeing
and trying to write an experiment that
replays that that's interesting stuff
try to go focus on value don't focus on
just
breaking things because it's not about
breaking it it's about
fixing it it's about remember we're
trying to create order we're not trying
to create cash that's what's so
that's why chaos casey and i for america
we don't even use the word chaos
engineering
people already know where the wrote the
rally books on it like they don't
already know who we are
but it's like we talk about in terms of
continuous verification right because
that's what it's about in our opinion
it's about consistently verifying the
system works the way it's supposed to
post appointment
and we find that language is a little
easier sometimes because people get
caught up in the chaos and
there's some companies out there just
talk about breaking things in production
just don't do that because like i'm
pretty sure you won't have a job very
long if you go around doing that
exactly and it kind of goes back to
where we discussed earlier with
you know designing your experiments look
at your previous incident data
base it off of reality because when you
go and we're going to discuss this a
little bit when we talk about
integrating it into the organization
but when you go in front of an executive
you want to be able to say like
we did this experiment because we've
seen this happen
500 times and it's had this amount of
business impact in this amount of cost
so by spending the money on this we've
solved a problem and saved money in the
future
but i do want to dive a little bit into
chaos slinger and you
did describe a little bit of the high
level architecture but can you
dive a little deeper into how that tool
actually worked
sure so if you go to chaos so casting
your spell
c-h-a-o-s-l-i-n-g-r
right all the internet people spell it
so differently just
it's on github uh it's um i've left the
united health group almost three and a
half years ago
or well three years ago so like i'm not
there to maintain that tool so
it's since become an internal tool but
the main tool that we use
we built is still out there they just
now i think they've integrated into
their pipelines i'm not sure what
they're doing how they're using it
but like um but anyway um the basic
framework for the tool
is there there's also on there there's a
there's a flow
of how the experiment actually functions
for portzlaner uh because when we open
sourced it
we wanted a base example that everyone
understood that's where the port slinger
example came from
is that like a software engineer a
firewall engineer network engineer
security engineer a database engineer
everybody knows what a firewall is
right um so uh but what it did was so
there is there were
i always messed this up i used amy
schoen was she was one of the lead
engineers
on helping me write the tool uh she
always said aaron oh there's four
functions
so i always used to say this three but
like there is uh
there is um uh there's generator there
is slinger
there's tracker and then the fourth
function is documentation
right so uh you know you have to
document what the experiment is supposed
to do
um so um what generator does what is
what it is
is so it uh our tool most chaos
engineering tools least open source ones
out there or most in general
have some kind of um opt-in opt-out
functionality right for us we use aws
tags
we have reference tags we use reference
tags to be like you know
so the tool for casting was originally
called pluslinger right so
that's no i think i've said this on a
podcast before but like because i mean
it was it was a it was a fun project it
was off the side of our desk
originally you know uh and you know
even the grown adults talk about that
stuff
anyway um no but uh so what it did was
is it is it is it uh
it went out and looked for uh security
groups with that tag
uh and it would either open or close a
port that was not already open or closed
i'd immediately open and close it right
we didn't open it leave it open right we
immediately closed we created the change
behavior
right uh and some some people use a
little bit differently but that was kind
of basic construct of it
uh but the the tool that made the change
was actually slinger slinger is
it was the tool that actually went out
and made the change uh and then tracker
would track
the change uh and report it report the
status of it into slack
because when we wrote it that was the
easiest way we didn't want emails or
more logs we just want to be able to
kind of understand
you know what happened so we could
address it um and you know that that was
the basis of it and and
you know we learned a lot in just that
basic experiment we were a few other
experiments one around s3 buckets and
iam roll collisions you know i one of
the most
interesting areas of exploration for uh
aws uh security cast experiments is the
fabric within the fabric
i am iam is the ghost in the machine in
aws
it's one of the most difficult things to
keep track of and with the easiest
things that cause a breach
you know so if you're looking for areas
to experiment at aws iem
is full of opportunity yeah identity as
a whole
is especially with modern systems it
it's critical that you understand that
but one other question that i have for
you when it comes to tooling
how should you integrate your chaos
engineering
tool or your security chaos engineering
tools with your other security tools or
development tooling
you know uh they're you know obviously
want to be able to integrate it
um you know you can integrate it in with
your logging solutions
um you know uh jira uh jira or whatever
ticketing solution you're using i see a
lot of people doing that
you know um they're actually i know some
uh some companies out there that like
require you to run experiments before
you submit a ticket to the the help desk
for the for the platform
i like to ensure that like the basics
you've that you see that you've
like okay you've done what you've done
everything you said you've done is
actually true
right um and i've seen that and people
put the output into jira
uh or like you know if experiment bills
can go to jira and
go through the process of remediation
through jira we can track it and then
you know you can put the status again of
like run the experiment again
right and then you can you can track
kind of what happened that's a valuable
way to kind of track lineage
and value of experiments and metrics and
measurement
um you know uh but really the ticketing
the observability
type of tools are kind of you know
obviously
um you know there's probably some
overlaps in the vulnerability management
but like
i don't know how many people are doing
that okay so essentially it's really
just around the
tracking of your experiment failure
success and then
remediating that and tracking that
remediation to show value
correct yeah i mean that's really what
we're trying to achieve and do you know
and obviously when the experiments fail
from that we get to that automated
regression a set of maturity
right that's also a great way to keep
track of that and measure that and
you know i mean it doesn't have to be
jira it could be any flavor of tool in
that space
but like um just gives us a capture
mechanism a learning mechanism a way of
you know obviously fall on maturity
progression
exactly and it gives you that option you
know if you decide that you want to
break the build for
a regression or something to that effect
now you can just integrate that and
handle it all in one place
changing directions here let's talk
about actually
selling security chaos engineering to
your organization
if you want to adopt it let's say you
listen to this podcast or you read the
book and you say this sounds like a
great idea let's do it
who do you think should lead getting
that into the organization
i could tell you from what experience
what i've seen right like
is like i mean i could make up stuff all
day i mean so i
so i wrote a whole section on this for
the like kelly and i wrote like there's
an extra 140 pages we wrote for that the
book we just released uh but like they
got cut because it could only be 90
pages
uh but it's gonna be this we have a
whole section on this in the book that's
coming out this year
maybe do some articles on it too because
it's a key thing uh is like
you know how do i sell this but like
like i said before
most people uh that are really it's
either
uh sres chaos enduring in general sres
kind of are best positioned uh
because that's what they do is they're
focused on slos they're focused on
uptime availability performance security
right you're seeing you're seeing really
security and sres becoming a combined
discipline
and that's been happening over the last
few years i think that's a trend that
continues
just like the devsecops stuff security
is usually five years later out of that
equation
you know but sre and security are
perfect match
um so sres your security operations
folks are good
but really what i'm really seeing is i'm
seeing the um
the architecture for security architects
like uh
usually they're um a lot of them are
very competent engineers
especially the software security
architecture spaces they're the ones
that understand
they usually come from some solar
software engineering background so they
kind of understand kind of what we're
doing while we're doing the basic
problem and
changing and building in context around
security uh
and uh but what i'm seeing people
adopting and making the case
is because a lot of times the architects
um you know
uh they're well positioned from a
organization perspective to
communicate to executives why they're
doing something the value of it
uh how effective control matters to them
you know um and
obviously sometimes they're involved in
cost measures as well and thinking about
that kind of thing
yeah so it's just they're as you've seen
it they've been
in a position where they're in a good
communication spot with the business
compared to some of the other
groups within the organization it's not
that they're necessarily
the best ones to do it it's just that
that's generally where it comes out of
well i would also i'll be at one thing
to that it's like
you know outside of the role persona
it's really about like
but the data will speak loud enough if
you make if you so if you start with a
very simple case and you run it on your
exp you run it on your environment and
then like you know you demonstrate that
i've always found a lot of value in like
something built is better than something
said
right like so you build it you try it
you do it and you see what results you
get from it
use the results to communicate what
happened like uh and i think that
also is a great way i mean that's an
obvious thing but i just want to state
that
that like that's also a great way to get
started in doing it
because it'll build you'll build a
momentum other people resonate with a
problem
and if you're having that problem
probably everybody else have the same
problem
exactly another question that you
generally hear
at least on the security space is how
does this meet some kind of compliance
requirement
is there any benefit in that space that
you see with security ks engineering
absolutely right like so that was one of
the biggest things i brought to the
chaos engineering space originally right
it's like
it's like hey guys you chaos i was like
the blessed but i was like the black
sheep originally with chaos engineering
like so i started doing stuff with cass
slinger right then i went out to netflix
casey invited me up to netflix and said
hey
what is this thing you guys you're doing
oh i'm doing the same thing you're doing
it for security and i'm explaining to
the next books to give my friend jason
chan and
netflix i'm explaining him like hey you
this is what chaos engineering does is
how you use it for security
i'm at netflix explaining to the
security team kind of how you can use
chaos and dream for security
and explaining how a safe day to the
chaos it was just
hilarious experience but one of the like
that i was just kind of addressing the
engineering
aspects of it but like every chaos
experiment
has compliance value because essentially
what you're doing
is you're proving whether the technology
worked the way
you thought it did right or how how you
had it documented
right whether it's availability or not
our security like
that's an audible artifact do you have
right there right like if it worked
like you don't have to go run it run
like all you have to do is
map that that uh experiment to a control
framework so if you use pci
use nist use hipaa use high trust use
bad wrap whatever it is
you map it to like uh au 1 or
or whatever whatever control it is you
map it and then you've got a control
uh that has audit data on a frequent
basis especially when you get to that
stage where you start automating the
regression type now you constantly got
an auto artifact that's great for
because because a lot of your auditors
out there now are not
not allowing you to have like
screenshots and and very subjective
types of evidence they want
actual instrumentation and data that is
not potentially fraudulent or
manipulative
or pri or manipulated prior to giving
giving it to them does that make sense
like they want they want to know that
like hey this system is meeting its
needs
exactly it's they want to see the
evidence that you're actually doing the
continuous monitoring that you say
you're doing and that you're
doing your disaster recovery and bcp
proofs
like you say you are and that you're
continuously validating that you're
doing all of these things that you say
you're doing not just
well i did a day i sent you the
screenshot oh exactly
exactly and then just one more thing can
you give
a couple examples of where you've seen a
successful you know security chaos
engineering implementation and
organization definitely
and so there are a couple use cases
actually in the in the book we just
released one from capital one
uh and one from cardinal health cardinal
health is like you know
it was fun for me as a so starting as a
startup like
you know actually just prior to starting
america like i had rob newhart and he's
not google
uh but he um he called me up and said
hey i was at rsa at the time he's like
uh he wasn't there at rc he's like hey
you know this whole security cast thing
how do you do it right because
i and then you know he ended up building
a whole program they call it applied
security
at cardinal health jamie dicken the heat
of hiring jimmy dickens she's the one
who actually build out the program
build off the team that writes all the
experiments and you know she's been
doing a lot of talks
out there so you can go on the internet
and check youtube and check out what
like what she's she's remarkable
she's uh she's done some really cool
things with security kiosks engineering
i think she does a lot of things around
containers as well uh also capital one
capital one uh david leveso
they call it uh cyber chaos engineering
he started with alerts you know and
making sure that they're learning
their controls were alerting and and
that the alerts were um
effective on the the controls that they
put in place that's kind of where he
started
he sort of branched out from there
because he actually he actually started
in the cyber test kitchen at capital one
and evaluating new technologies
right and then you're using some breach
attack simulation tools for that
throwing attack
solutions but then he's like hey why am
i evaluating all the
like the effectiveness of like new tools
why am i not seeing how effective what
we have now is
maybe what we have now is worth knowing
how good that is before we buy something
right like so so that's what made him
like sort of drift into like okay i'm
gonna try this security chaos thing
and start introducing some of these
basics into the system to see
how effective they are and find out
maybe where the gaps are maybe where
they should buy things
you know um so there's two great uh
they're gonna expand their use cases in
the main in the book maybe some more
companies come online they're gonna
share their stories um and uh but
capital one cardinal health i'd watch i
watch what they're doing
they're doing some very successful
things over there yeah and i'll
definitely compile some resources from
both of those groups and add them to the
show notes that way listeners have a
couple videos to go watch if they want
to
learn a little bit more about these
things just to wrap up the show though
is there anything that i missed or
didn't cover in here that you think
a software engineer should know well i'd
say that
it's important to recognize a couple
things right um
the brittleness in your system can never
be zero
it always exists your system will always
be somewhat brittle
right the idea is to try to find out
where it is before
it causes pain or an issue um and i
would say the second thing
to to note is that uh and this is more
from the security
software security perspective or
security in general is that you know
remember that security is a human
construct it takes humans to
it takes humans to create it right so
it's reliability quality most abilities
are human created
so we're just pointing at the finger at
a human or an engineer doesn't solve
anything
it just points a finger you know so so
those are the two major points i guess i
would
make i feel passionate about i guess
fantastic and i know you've mentioned
the new o'reilly book that you're
working on is there anything else that
you're also working on now yeah so one i
i
spent a lot of time with verica spent a
lot of time in the book with kelly uh
and research-wise i'm really i'm really
digging the work from dr david woods
uh on the human side of cyber security
you check it out on youtube
it was um it was just a couple weeks ago
that it came out but like
he is david woods if you're not familiar
with him he is one of the
leaders in resilience engineering he
came from i mean he started with three
mile island
he's been helping john allspa and
richard cook
apply that body of research to cyber
security
and that's what there's so much you can
learn from the fields of
resilience engineering safety
engineering and cognitive systems
engineering and applying that to how we
do
modern software security it's amazing
the amount of
insights and learning you can apply to
increase value
and learning those things yeah and i'll
definitely include a link to the
human side of cyber security there in
the show notes for the listeners if they
want to go refer to that video
i just want to thank you for coming on
the show aaron it's been great
discussing security chaos engineering
with you
it's an absolute pleasure thank you very
much for having me yeah of course
this is justin baier for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
you